A Finding Aid to the Paul Allen Reed Papers, 1936-2008, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Paul Allen Reed papers
1936-2008
Archives of American Art
Reed, Paul, 1919-2015
AAA.reedpaul
Archival Resource Key
1.5 Linear feet
0.774 Gigabytes
The Paul Allen Reed papers measure 1.5 linear feet and 0.774 GB and date from 1936 to 2008. The papers document Reed's career as a painter through correspondence with friends and colleagues; writings by Reed including lecture notes and teaching plans; professional files including binders with curriculum vitae and cataloged artwork, and sound, video, and born-digital recordings including interviews; printed material such as clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs; studies for paintings; and photographs of Reed and his artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The Paul Allen Reed papers measure 1.5 linear feet and 0.774 GB and date from 1936 to 2008. The papers document Reed's career as a painter through correspondence with friends and colleagues; writings by Reed including lecture notes and teaching plans; professional files including binders with curriculum vitae and cataloged artwork, and sound, video, and born-digital recordings including interviews; printed material such as clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs; studies for paintings; and photographs of Reed and his artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Painter Paul Allen Reed (1919-2015) was born, and lived for most of his life, in Washington, D.C. He was a member of the Washington Color School, whose style of abstract color-field painting emerged and flourished in the city's art scene during the 1960s.
Reed taught at the Corcoran School of Art from 1971 to the early 1980s. His work can be found in the collections of the National Gallery of Art, the Smithsonian American Art Museum, the Art Institute of Chicago, and other museums.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Paul Allen Reed papers were donated by Paul Reed between 1995 and 2008.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1963-2007 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings, 1966-1981 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Professional Activity Files, 1936-2008 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1963-2007 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1, 0.774 GB; ER01)
Series 5: Artwork, 1952-1990 (0.7 linear feet; Box 1-3)
Series 6: Photographic Material, 1964-2008 (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history with Paul Reed conducted by Judith Zilczer, April 29, 1994.
Sound recordings; Interviews; Video recordings; Painters -- Washington (D.C.); Washington Color School (Group of artists); Educators -- Washington (D.C.)
- Correspondence, 1963-2007; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence consists of letters, primarily in the form of photocopies, from museums and galleries regarding the purchase and/or exhibition of Reed's artwork. Also found is correspondence between Reed and Claudine Humblet, mostly concerning research for Humblet's book, The New American Abstraction, 1950-1970.
  - Correspondence, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Claudine Humblet, 1993-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1966-1981; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include Reed's teaching plans and notes, including for the Corcoran School of Art, as well as unpublished writing about Reed by others.
  - By Paul Reed, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - By Others, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Corcoran School of Art Class Lectures, 1973-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Professional Activity Files, 1936-2008; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1; 0.774 Gigabytes ER01
  Professional material includes two binders cataloging Reed's artwork and some biographical material. Audiovisual material includes a 1969 sound recording of Reed and Roger Selby responding to a letter by Ellen Gross; a sound recording of a 1985 interview of Reed conducted by Ed Zerne; a video recording showing Reed's artwork in reverse chronological order from 1992 to 1936; and a digital video recording with images of art and Reed discussing his career.
  - Biographical Information, 1936-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Binder #1, 2008; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER01 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Binder consists of printed copies of artwork, and curriculum vitae.
  - Binder #2, 2008; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital records, see ER01 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Paintings, Sculptures, Photographs, and Prints 1952 through 2008, Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 0.774 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER01)
  - Paul Reed Catalog of Artwork, 1993; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    A reverse chronology of Reed's works starting from 1992 and going back to 1952.
  - Paul Reed Interviewed by Ed Zerne, 1985; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Paul Reed and Roger Selby in Response to Ellen Gross Lecture, 1969; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Printed Material, 1963-2007; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material includes exhibition catalogs, photocopies of clippings, and a set of playing cards featuring a work of art by Reed, published by the Women's Committee of the Wadsworth Athenaeum.
  - Clippings, 1963-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16-19)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1963-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Double Deck of Playing Cards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Artwork, 1952-1990; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Works of art consist of approximately 128 original studies for Reed's works in various media.
  - Studies for Paintings, 1952-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-45)
  - Studies for Paintings, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Studies for Paintings, 1952-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Studies for Quad Photos, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographic Material, 1964-2008; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Series consists of photographs of Reed and photographs, slides, and digital photos of his works of art. Digital photos may be copies of photographs that were printed out for Binder #1 and Binder #2 found in Series 3: Professional Activity Files.
  - Photographs of Paul Reed, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Works of Art, 1976-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6-9)
  - Slides of Works of Art, 1964-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Digital Photographs, 2008; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 2, Folder 11)